<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A strange and wonderfull prognostication: or rather, prenomination of those accidents which shall, or at least are likely to happen as may be coniectured by the rules and directions of astrology, in this yeare 1624. Written by Anthonio Magini, an Italian professor of the mathematickes, and much experienced in astonomy. And now faithfully translated into English.</title>
            <author>Magini, Giovanni Antonio, 1555-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06739</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17183</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102728</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838495</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838495</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2876</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06739)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2876)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 811:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A strange and wonderfull prognostication: or rather, prenomination of those accidents which shall, or at least are likely to happen as may be coniectured by the rules and directions of astrology, in this yeare 1624. Written by Anthonio Magini, an Italian professor of the mathematickes, and much experienced in astonomy. And now faithfully translated into English.</title>
                  <author>Magini, Giovanni Antonio, 1555-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By E. Allde?] for Nathanael Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Print faded and show-through; some pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2876:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2876:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A STRANGE AND WONDERFVLL Prognoſtication: Or rather, PRENOMINATION of thoſe Accidents which ſhall, or at leaſt are likely to happen, as may be conie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured by the heauenly Influences; Foretelling the wondrous direfull Euents which ſhall fall out in all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as may be collected by the Rules and Directions of Aſtrology, in this yeare 1624.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Anthonio Magini,</hi> an Italian Profeſſor of the Mathematickes, and much experienced in Aſtronomy: And now faithfully tranſlated into Engliſh.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> for <hi>Nathanael Butter.</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:2876:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2876:2"/>
            <head>The Preface, ſhewing in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner this Kalender or Prognoſtication is to be vnderſtood.</head>
            <p>TO come to our Almanacke and Prognoſtication, which hath aboue two hundred declarations or points, and therefore if the one halfe, or the fourth part, be but true it will be well.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, it is to bee vnderſtood, that the things happen not iuſt the ſame time, houre, or day they are predicted, but are deferred ſometimes for a little while; for you know that water in a Kettle hanged on the fire boyles not preſently, and euen ſo is it with the operation of the Planets or Signes of the Firmament.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſmall proofe of the laſt yeare. 1623.</head>
               <p>Sayd hee not what was to happen betwixt the <hi>Rhyne, Elbe,</hi> and <hi>Weſer,</hi> and in the Northerne parts of the world?</p>
               <p>Did he not likewiſe ſpeake of a Match, as alſo where the warre ſhould be, and how farre it ſhould extend?</p>
               <p>Hee predicted likewiſe a battell of a certaine Prince, and the defeat of his ſouldiers vpon the thirteenth of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt, of which the Boers of <hi>Weſtphalia</hi> ſhould tel ſtrange things.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe he talked much of treaſon, and of a ſimul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated peace, as is knowne to <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Hungary.</hi> And
<pb facs="tcp:2876:3"/>
made alſo mention of the Forces that ſhould march vpon the frontier of <hi>Turky</hi> and <hi>Hungary,</hi> deſigning the inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Bethlem Gabor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreouer, hee predicted alſo that the plague ſhould reigne mightily in the Northerne Lands, as hath after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards beene ſeene in <hi>Polonia, Lituania, Sweden,</hi> and <hi>Eaſt-Frieſland,</hi> in which lands there died aboue 200000 perſons of the Sickneſſe.</p>
               <p>Obſerue likewiſe what he ſaith of the dearth, the like being hardly knowne by any man now liuing.</p>
               <p>And concerning the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> haue not the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants made ſuch an inuaſion in it as was neuer done before.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe we will not forget that which he told of the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> and of the great alteration in the Romane Empire.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, hee predicted that the Northerne Lands ſhould want both bread and wine, which ſeemed to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely, ſeeing it was a fertile yeare, and that all the fruits of the field were ripe, and caried into the barnes, and there was alſo great ſtore of fiſh catcht, vpon which acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent the prices of al other victuals are vſed to fal, but the dearth increaſed dayly againſt all expectation.</p>
               <p>He ſayth alſo that about the Harueſt or Auguſt, many ſhould be ſlaine vpon the frontiers of <hi>Hungary.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2876:3"/>
            <head>Here beginneth the Italian Sooth-ſayer, or Prognoſtication, practiſed by <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonio Magini,</hi> Profeſſor of the Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matickes at Bononia in Italy.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Ianuarie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He yeares in former times took not their beginning as they do now,
<note place="margin">
                     <list>
                        <item>a 1. <hi>Circ. of Chr.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>b 2. <hi>Steph. oct.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>c 3. <hi>S. Ioh oct.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>d 4. <hi>Titus.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>e 5. <hi>Edward</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>f 6. <hi>Three Kings.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </note>
for ſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan it when the Sun was in the midſt of the Firmament; and others, when it was neereſt vnto them; and we make the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of it when the Sunne is furtheſt from vs, to wit, in <hi>Capricornus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that our Winter beginneth vpon the the 22 of September. And I find, hauing ouer-looked all the celeſtiall Signes, that <hi>Saturnus</hi> and <hi>Iupiter</hi> going into <hi>Leo,</hi> goe backwards as the Crabs doe, <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, Venus</hi> and <hi>Mercurius</hi> in <hi>Sagitarius,</hi> and <hi>Luna</hi> neere at hand, trauelling as a meſſenger vp and down; when the Moone ſhall be in <hi>Taurus,</hi> and begin to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, then we ſhall haue the eight after the birth of Chriſt, and the ſame is the firſt day of the yeare, and ſhal be gouerned as followeth, by the power of God.</p>
               <p>The 5, being full Moone, are <hi>Saturnus</hi> and <hi>Iupiter</hi> declared Lords of this yere, &amp; <hi>Luna</hi> is alſo to be an aid of them. And firſt to ſpeake of her gouernment,

<note place="margin">
                     <list>
                        <head>Sunday.</head>
                        <item>G 7. <hi>Valentius.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>a 8. <hi>Erhardus.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>b 9. <hi>Iulianus.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>c 10. <hi>Paulus her.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>d 11. <hi>Higinus pa.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>e 12. <hi>Benedictus.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>f 13. <hi>Hilar. Epiſ.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </note> ſhe ſhal cauſe a cold, vnhealthfull, deare, &amp; miſerable time.</p>
               <p>Concerning <hi>Saturnus,</hi> hee ſhall alſo vſe his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted cruelty, and goe about to ſpoile euen the child in the Cradle; and in ſeuerall places, as vpon the height of 48 and 53 degrees, doe great hurt, as in <hi>Bohemia,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2876:4"/>Hungary, Morauia, Sileſia, Germany, Polonia,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countries bordering vpon the <hi>Low-Countries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <list>
                        <head>Sunday.</head>
                        <item>G 14. <hi>Pontian.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>a 15. <hi>Jeſus nam.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>b 16 <hi>Marcellus.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>c 17. <hi>Anton. op.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>d 18. <hi>Priſc. virg.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>e 19. <hi>Herental.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>f 20. <hi>Fab. Sebaſt.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </note>
The 13, with the laſt quarter of the Moone, is <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Piſces,</hi> which is certainly an ill ſigne (for bad trees giue bad fruits, &amp; lame meſſengers bring bad newes) and he cauſeth the Sea to bee ſet on fire, through the power of <hi>Neptunus,</hi> and ſhall alſo goe about to breake the Peace, which could be concluded in theſe times, making great ſteps euen into the Indies, and incites the <hi>Waterlanders</hi> (or <hi>Hollanders</hi>) to the battell, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them all the riches of the world, ſo that many na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Europe</hi> ſhall hearken to him, being deſirous to be deliuered from the cryes of the hungry, and to find a better Country then they inhabit.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <list>
                        <head>Sunday.</head>
                        <item>G 21. <hi>S Agneta.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>a 22. <hi>Vincentius.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>b 23. <hi>Emerent.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>c 24 <hi>Timotheus.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>d 25. <hi>Pauls co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>u.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>e 26. <hi>Policarpus.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>f 27. <hi>Ioh. Chriſoſt.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </note>
The 20, with the full Moone, was <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curius</hi> aboue the head of <hi>Sagitarius,</hi> the one being ſomewhat whoriſh, and the other ſomewhat knauiſh. About this time will much treaſon and deceit bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and that ſhall euen come from lands that lye farre off at the other ſide of Hell, ſeeing that <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer</hi> reigneth, therefore looke to your ſelfe, ſo ſhall it happen that the Crane ſhall inuite the Fox, who ſhall find himſelfe deceiued at laſt.</p>
               <p>The 27, being the firſt quarter of the Moone, ought his Holineſſe to looke a little to the Alpes, for there ſhall ſtrange ſignes be ſeene, and many conſpirations be made with them of S. <hi>Marck</hi> (the <hi>Venetians.</hi>)</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:2876:4"/>The 28 commeth the Sunne into <hi>Aquarius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <list>
                        <head>Sunday.</head>
                        <item>G 28. <hi>Carol. Mag</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>a 29. <hi>Valerius.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>b 30. <hi>Septuageſ.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>c 31. <hi>Iſaac.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </note> who running ſwiftly to the warre, in the hot Countries, ſeemes to confirm the former, leauing the cold coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries behind infeſted or vexed with famine, pyracies, and inundations.</p>
               <p>The laſt of this Moneth ſhall <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Mercurius</hi> be oppoſite, as likewiſe <hi>Saturnus</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> and there was a ſtrange tricke played, but it ſeemed not cleanly to be done. But <hi>Luna</hi> although ſhee was in <hi>Cancer</hi> came neuertheleſſe to them which dwell vnder the Creuice, namely, the Sea-cocks, and brought tydings that Shield-bearer would ayd them vpon the fronti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Turky.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>February.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <list>
                        <item>d 1. <hi>Bridget.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>e 2. <hi>Marie.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>f 3. <hi>Blaſius Biſh.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <head>Sunday.</head>
                        <item>G 4. <hi>Rembertus.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>a 5. <hi>Agatha.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>b 6. <hi>Dorothea.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>c 7. <hi>Richardus.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>d 8. <hi>Salomon.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>e 9. <hi>Apolonia.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>f 10. <hi>Ireneus.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </note>THe 4, being full Moone, is the Sunne yet in <hi>Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> and <hi>Saturnus,</hi> and <hi>Iupiter</hi> in <hi>Leo,</hi> and doe not ceaſe yet from running theſe ill courſes, and to vſe ill deuices, to take the gold from one another, giuing iron onely in lieu of it; which newes being brought into <hi>Spaine,</hi> vpon 35 degrees it will cauſe great murmure and diſcontentment. And <hi>Iupiter</hi> ſhall goe about to remedie it by the meanes of his goodneſſe, and make many friends with gifts, whereby the purſe will bee emptied, neuertheleſſe he will keepe counſell.</p>
               <p>The 11, being the laſt quarter, was <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Aries,</hi> or
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2876:5"/>
in the hurting Ram, walking very deſperately, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that his children vnder the gouernment of <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> and <hi>Iupiter,</hi> in the Northerne parts of <hi>Europe</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered famine, and that hee would reuenge it in the South. To which effect hee had cauſed the Fleet of <hi>Neptune</hi> to be gathered together by <hi>Triton,</hi> &amp; would himſelfe in perſon viſit the caſhes of <hi>India,</hi> to relieue his children with them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <list>
                        <head>Sunday.</head>
                        <item>G 11. <hi>Deſiderius.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>a 12. <hi>Gandent.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>b 13. <hi>Tranquil.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>c 14. <hi>Valentius.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>d 15. <hi>Craton. mar</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>e 16. <hi>Iuliana.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>f 17. <hi>Conſtantia.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </note>This ſhall cauſe ioy on the one ſide, and heauineſſe on the other, for there breedeth continually quarrell whereſoeuer is queſtion made of hauing &amp; keeping: for the one ſhall thinke that by reaſon of his long poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, anothers good is his own. Therefore ye Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders looke too that through treaſon you bee not fruſtrated of your deſigne.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <list>
                        <head>Sunday.</head>
                        <item>G 18. <hi>Simon biſh</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>a 19. <hi>Sabinus.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>b 20. <hi>Gallus con.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>c 21 <hi>Coronat.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>d 22. <hi>S. Peters.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>e 23. <hi>Biſſext. cor.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>f 24.</item>
                     </list>
                  </note>The 18, being new Moone, was <hi>Venus</hi> in <hi>Capricor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and gaue order to <hi>Mercurius</hi> that he ſhould looke to his buſineſſe, and play his part well, ſeeing that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt the gods were out of their owne houſes, ſeeking helpe and ayd of other, and eſpecially betwixt 35 and 46 degrees. And the Bird of <hi>Iupiter</hi> had loſt many of her chiefeſt feathers, and hee ſent to the Peacocke and the white Eagle, to borrow other feathers to ayd himſelfe in time of neceſſity with flying. By this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent meeting are vnderſtood all the allies of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the Emperor and all his States, but concerning their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund it is yet vncertaine whether they ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it.</p>
               <p>The 19 commeth the Sunne into <hi>Piſces,</hi> which is a good ſigne for the Fiſhers, but ill for them that goe to catch Birds.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:2876:5"/>Betwixt the 23 and 24 you ſhall find this yeare a day to be remoued, and it is certaine that nothing is ſtedfaſt without alteration or commotion, and euen in ſuch manner ſhall the heauineſſe remoue from the one place to the other: and if it ſhould bee told vnto which they ſhould happen, it would but bereaue them of their ioy. The Gods to preuent all this, had cauſed <hi>Argus</hi> with his 100 eyes to keepe watch. But <hi>Mercurius</hi> hauing cut off his head, preſented the eies vnto the Bird of <hi>Iune,</hi> which is the Peacocke, whom the Gods haue ſet on the high Mountaines to watch what <hi>Auſtria, Germany, Italy, France, England,</hi> the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> and <hi>Polen,</hi> doe.</p>
               <p>The 25, being the firſt quarter, the <hi>Hollanders</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue tydings of their victories in foraine Countries. And <hi>Luna</hi> was in <hi>Cancer,</hi> which is her water Creuice, and is a good ſigne for them; and when it happens to her, that decreaſed mightily the Romiſh Empire. Therefore looke to yourſelfe, that you ſhew them in the dreame through the Angell of <hi>Iacob,</hi> another way into the Empire, yea euen with a play in Lent, but take heed of the end.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:2876:6"/>
               <head>March.</head>
               <p>THe 5, with the full Moone, was <hi>Saturne</hi> ſtill in the middeſt of heauen in the fiery Lyon, and <hi>Iupiter</hi> walked vp and downe on the ſame height, intending to aſſwage the former anger of the Lyon, but he min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſomething elſe, ſeeing that <hi>Sol</hi> came toward him, ſo that all the Elements ſhewed their power to goe towards the Northerne places of the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> whereupon the Sunne, Moone, Windes, and Waters droue with great force vnder the Aequator or Line towards the Iſlands of <hi>Cuba</hi> and <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> euen in ſuch manner that many did maruell at it. And <hi>Iupiter,</hi> who would ſhew his power, loſt a piece of his beard, thinking onely to ſtay the ſtreames: but alas, it was in vaine, ſeeing that <hi>Iupiter</hi> (whoſe Maſts reach vnto the skies) was himſelfe in the Fleet which caried in her co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours Batauia and a Lyon) whom <hi>Iupiter</hi> thought to tye ſo faſt that he ſhould not be able to moue a vaine, but he loſt idlely his labour.</p>
               <p>The 12 being the laſt quarter, <hi>Iupiter</hi> commanded his Bird the Eagle, to take the pan by the tayle to look how many egges the Boers threw into the pan; and to learne his ſubiects to liue ſparingly, in Lent, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon many were blacke and ſtarued.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:2876:6"/>O poore husbandmen that liue betwixt the Eaſt and the blacke Sea, and eſpecially you that liue about the riuers of Elbe, Weſer, Rhyne, and Donow. In the ſame time was <hi>Mars</hi> in the houſe of Death, namely, in <hi>Taurus,</hi> or the wild Bull, with his ſteeled or ſtrong hornes, vſing there ſuch violence, that hee will make mankind almoſt weary of their liues. And euen in the ſame time there ſhall alſo be a Baſiliſque or Cokatrice that ſhall brood egges, of which the young ones ſhall be ſeene in many places. <hi>Venus</hi> was in <hi>Aquarius,</hi> and <hi>Luna</hi> in <hi>Capricornus,</hi> all the Planets being in ſtrange houſes, which ſurely betokens ſome ſtrange thing, as the Starres alſo of the Eaſt, South, and North paſſage vpon the height of the Spaniſh and Netherlandiſh Seas. Towards <hi>Turky</hi> and <hi>France</hi> is alſo ſomething ſeene which is not pleaſing to the Gods.</p>
               <p>The 19 being new Moone, there is alſo about <hi>Mexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> or <hi>Noua Hiſpania</hi> a darkneſſe in the Sunne ſeene, which wil cauſe great alteration in thoſe lands, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in <hi>Congo,</hi> the red Sea, <hi>Goa,</hi> and other places of the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> for they are almoſt all vpon one cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate.</p>
               <p>The Sun comming into <hi>Aries,</hi> there ſhall a ſtrange and wonderfull ioy be heard, and night and day ſhall then be of one length, and the graines in the Northern parts ſhall be ſold better cheape then they were at the laſt Harueſt when all the barnes were full.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:2876:7"/>The 26, being the laſt quarter, there ſhall at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the ſweet time be ſpoken of great warlike preparations, but they ſhall not all come to effect, by reaſon of ſome ſmall Gods (vnderſtand thereby neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trall Princes) neuertheleſſe there ſhall vpon the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time a Fleet of <hi>Neptune</hi> be ſet abroad, and he that ſhall goe with it vnder the earth, ſhall haue good ſucceſſe, for the Sunne is in a good Climate, and this is likewiſe a fertile yeare in generall, few Countries onely excepted, in which ſhall deadly vapours and miſts riſe out of the earth, and poyſon both fields and trees, and are ſhortly euen againſt nature out of the Eaſt to come into the Weſt, contrary to the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned courſe of the Firmament.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:2876:7"/>
               <head>April.</head>
               <p>THe 3, being full Moone, are <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Iupiter</hi> yet in <hi>Leo,</hi> and puffed vp with pride, thought the Kings Houſe to bee their owne: vpon the ſame day towards the euening they were on a ſudden afraid, for there happened in the 10 degree of <hi>Libra,</hi> a darkneſſe in the Moone by reaſon of a faintneſſe ſhee fell in, as ſhall be ſeene in <hi>Europe,</hi> and ſhall laſt aboue 3 houres. During this darkneſs there ſhal be ſome traytors who ſhall ſeeke to couer or excuſe themſelues, and many theeues ſhall ſeeke to bring their bootie into other Lands, and many ſcores ſhall not bee paid, by reaſon of ſudden ſickneſſe.</p>
               <p>The tenth, being the laſt quarter, when the egges of Eaſter ſhall be diuided, ſo ſhall <hi>Mars</hi> be in <hi>Gemini,</hi> which ſhall cauſe pitifull cries of diſarmed people, which ſhall howle and lament as women and children. Therfore ſeeing that <hi>Saturnus</hi> a deuourer of children, is Lord and Gouernor of this yeare, it will be beſt for the diſarmed and faint-hearted to giue themſelues in good time vnder a Protector who may defend them, or they may otherwiſe timely goe vnder the earth, and flye to the other world.</p>
               <p>The hot Feuers ſhall reigne mightily, and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the lands which haue great Riuers to runne to the Sea, for the waters ſhall be ſpoyled through bad
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2876:8"/>
confluences, and they that ſhall drinke of them ſhall ſuddenly die, looke then to the ſtreames of Donaw, Elbe, Weſer, Ems, Maſe, Rhyne, Schelde, Lore in <hi>France,</hi> and the Po in <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 17, being new Moone, you ſhall haue a dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Sun being yet in <hi>Piſces,</hi> and ſhall be ſeene by them which lie vnder the Meridian of <hi>Italy,</hi> as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by them which dwell about the Straights of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gellan,</hi> as the Patigones and other nations about them, where it ſhall doe his operation as well as in theſe parts.</p>
               <p>The 18 commeth the Sunne into <hi>Taurus,</hi> at which time there ſhall many goe to the warre, and the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants which haue great ſtore of munition prouided, may make then good cheare. <hi>Venus</hi> being then ſtill in <hi>Piſces,</hi> ſhe ſhal very cunningly ſeek to make a match, but ſhee and all her adherents ſhall get diſgrace for thanke. But on the other ſide, there ſhall the next mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſomething elſe appeare in the Northerne land, and ſhall be againſt the Romane Empire. Now huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen looke to it, for <hi>Mars</hi> is now in action, and <hi>Neptune</hi> goeth on with his reſolued enterpriſe, and commeth into a Country in which <hi>Ceres</hi> and <hi>Bacchus</hi> ſhall be honoured, neuertheleſſe keep your horſe ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, for ſome thinke to ſurpriſe you with an ambuſh, and to make hauocke of your goods. All manner of beaſts ſhall be ſold at deare rates vnder <hi>Taurus,</hi> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially about the Riuers of Ems, Rhyne, Weſer, and the Donow: But on the other ſide, they ſhall in the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> bee giuen for almoſt nothing, and there
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2876:8"/>
ſhall new Townes and Cities bee built by a Nation, whoſe eyes are as browne as the eyes of Whitings: and this ſhall bee done before the Sunne commeth againe into <hi>Taurus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>May.</head>
               <p>THe third (being full Moone) vpon Croſſe-day, was <hi>Saturne</hi> in the 12 degree, and <hi>Iupiter</hi> in the 22 degree aboue <hi>Leo,</hi> at great ſtrife, the one would haue it thus, and the other ſo: and in the meane time gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red S. <hi>Iacob</hi> his Schalpes: <hi>Iupiter</hi> would faine haue had peace to reſt himſelfe a while, but <hi>Saturnus</hi> would not condiſcend vnto it; whereupon <hi>Leo</hi> conſidering their debate, ſhewed the doore to them both, and gaue them leaue to walke. But <hi>Iupiter</hi> ſaw from aboue that the Eagle (his Bird) was in great diſtreſſe, and had a heauie croſſe on his necke or backe. This will with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion draw great miſery and calamity vpon <hi>Polonia, Germany,</hi> or ſome other parts of the Empire, vnleſſe there happen ſome alteration in <hi>Gemini,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 9, with the laſt quarter, was <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Gemini,</hi> and walked towards the Creuice, which can turne at the left and right ſide, and chiefly by water, and is with his armed Cizers to bring <hi>Mars</hi> ouer into the Weſt, for both the wind and ſtreame will fauour him. At the ſame time ſhall the <hi>Waterlander</hi> (or <hi>Hollander</hi>) haue good ſucceſſe by water, and eſpecially in ſome Lands which lye farre from his owne Country, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2876:9"/>
vnder another Climate, as likewiſe vnder this, but there is yet one new tiding to bee told, which time will reueale. At the ſame time ſhall <hi>Pegaſus</hi> beginne ſomething in the Northerne parts, about the height of <hi>Lituania</hi> and <hi>Polonia,</hi> where the King of the Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to make ſome great enterpriſe, and hangs the Eagle a ſhield or Skuſhion about the necke. And caſt now a little an eye vpon <hi>Tranſiluania,</hi> about the Flood <hi>Irydanus,</hi> the Peacocke hangs her tayle downe, and ſhall be deſtroyed by many children of <hi>Saturnus.</hi> The Lilies or Fleurs du lis riſe both about the ſides of the water, and in the Mountaines of <hi>Swiſſerland;</hi> and euen about the ſame time a moſt ioyfull tydings ſhall bee heard.</p>
               <p>The 17, being full Moone, <hi>Venus</hi> is on the Ram, and makes great haſte to come vpon <hi>Taurus</hi> that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned beaſt, meaning thereby <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luna</hi> is likewiſe ſeene in <hi>Taurus,</hi> but the Peacocke the Bird of <hi>Iuno</hi> can tell you how ſhe is pleaſed, looke but vpon her actions.</p>
               <p>The 20 beganne the ioyfull play, for <hi>Luna</hi> went from <hi>Gemini,</hi> and <hi>Sol</hi> came with his golden beames in her roome, and there ſhall bee heard a harmony of many inſtruments; <hi>Mercury</hi> plaies vpon his pipe, <hi>Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunus</hi> bloweth the horne of <hi>Triton,</hi> ſitting vpon the wooden horſe, and euery one did as hee was minded: <hi>Mars</hi> being yet in <hi>Gemini.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the meane time commeth <hi>Mathuſalem</hi> with the fearfull Deaths head, whoſe heires are Serpents, and they all dyed that ſaw it, therefore looke not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout at that time, but goe ſtraight on your wayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:2876:9"/>The fiue and twentieth, being the firſt Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, leapt <hi>Venus</hi> from <hi>Taurus</hi> and came in <hi>Gemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> in which the Sunne ranne her courſe, and would as well as the reſt eate of the banquet ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar: all ſweet Meates shall bee good cheape, and ſhee did eate ſo much of it, that her belly began to ſwell: but whether it bee now poyſon of Traytors, or that ſhee ſhall breed ſweete twinnes, you ſhall perceiue it vnder <hi>Virgo,</hi> by three that beareth Roſes, and if ſhee happen to reſt there; ſo ſhall it bee an ill time for them which were vſed to get their liuing vnder <hi>Mars,</hi> but neuertheleſſe they ſhall play the bride of Whitſontide, although there bee not an Eare or Graine in the Barnes, but they ſhall ſhake it, if it be not within it is without: <hi>Venus</hi> hauing in the meane time gotten her Horſes to her Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot, rides with a Thundry noyſe through the Ayre, vntill ſhee commeth in <hi>Leo;</hi> and if <hi>Mars</hi> bee not aſſwaged in this time, take your tooles in your bagge and walke to the Blacke Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Junius.</head>
               <p>THe firſt, being full Moone and all Fruites increaſing, <hi>Mars</hi> was ſicke or ſeemed or fained at leaſt to be ſo, hauing a cloath ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed abut his Head. And <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Iupiter</hi> were in <hi>Leo,</hi> and <hi>Sol</hi> in <hi>Gemini. Venus</hi> ſits now vpon <hi>Europa</hi> as a rider vpon his Horſe, and willing (with ſweet or wollen kiſſes which ſhee hath
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2876:10"/>
ſtolne from the lame) to ſet one of her friends vpon her <hi>(Europa)</hi> the Angels roſe out of their ſleepe, and tooke Roſes and Lillies in the hand. Whereupon all the branches of <hi>Bohemia</hi> (ſeeing that <hi>Luna</hi> was in <hi>Sagitarius</hi>) roſe vp. <hi>Mercurius</hi> played ſo well that ſome were fallen in a ſleepe, but if he keepes no better watch then <hi>Argus</hi> did, and continue his piping, all is ſpoyled, and hee ſits as dangerouſly as a Lowſe vpon a Combe.</p>
               <p>The 8. th, being the quarter of the Moone, were many Trees that ſtood very faire, but were not yet peeced about their nether-parts, and many fruits pulled on their bootes, with inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſee what doings there were abroad, but before they were almoſt ready, the Diuell was in ſuch a rage, that they had preſently in their Spring, their head bitten off by <hi>Taurus,</hi> and their rootes almoſt pulled out by <hi>Leo.</hi> Whereupon was <hi>Iupiter</hi> compelled to goe from <hi>Leo,</hi> and <hi>Saturnius</hi> followed him cloſe at his heeles. And <hi>Mars</hi> comming in the meane time in <hi>Cancer,</hi> was very much diſcontented, by reaſon that there were ſo many that had conſpired to kill him, and tolde to his Widowes, that hee was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine on horſebacke vnder <hi>Cancer,</hi> ſeeing he had gotten <hi>Mercurius</hi> on his owne ſide, and were running both in one ſpurre, (or tooke both one courſe) and would make it ſo, that the Calues-skinnes (young men hee meanes) ſhould ſuffer much.</p>
               <p>The 12. th, being new Moone, came <hi>Luna</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in <hi>Cancer.</hi> Conferring this time by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2876:10"/>
as I obſerued, that whenſoeuer they come ſo many Butchers in <hi>Cancer,</hi> that the Sea-cocks haue much winde in their head, and that euen to their owne good. Therefore looke to the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Pirats, the blacke Sea-cockes, and vpon the Gulfe of <hi>Venice,</hi> the Mediterranean Sea, and all Riuers that are Nauigable, as likewiſe vpon the Eaſt Sea, betwixt <hi>Polonia, Ruſsia,</hi> and <hi>Pruſen,</hi> and chiefly to the water called the <hi>Zouth</hi>-Sea, and ſee whether it ends not all in batteries or Battels; to bee briefe, they ſhall there euery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where bee in action, ſome publikely, and ſome priuatly, but you muſt not vnderſtand that it ſhall onely be on the Water, but they that ſhall Commaund ouer them ſhall put on their yron Gauntlets, fearing to be pinched of the <hi>Creuice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 15. th, ſhall there bee a Coniunction of <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> and they ſhall ſeeke to couer one another: When this ſhall happen I would wiſh the Husbandman not to pay his Rent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand, ſeeing that the Children of <hi>Mars</hi> will demaund it againe of them.</p>
               <p>Hereupon, ſo commeth <hi>Sol</hi> againe vpon the 19. th, with his golden armour in <hi>Cancer,</hi> and walketh ſo with <hi>Mars</hi> towards the Weſt. This is a ſigne, that <hi>Mars</hi> or his Meſſengers, ſhall get great booties of Gold and Siluer in the Weſt, and eſpecially they that are mencioned on the 12. th day heere before, and it ſhall goe as Ebbe and Flood, for that which is taken from the one ſhall be giuen to the other; Whither this will ſmart, you may euen by the Elements and her
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2876:11"/>
Children perceiue. To be briefe, the fortune of the one is the miſhap of the other.</p>
               <p>The 24. th, being the firſt Quarter, ſo ſhall the catchers of Crabbes get good returnes out of the Eaſt <hi>Indies,</hi> of a Treaſure that was long bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried betwixt <hi>Braſill</hi> and <hi>Guinea,</hi> about a banke on which <hi>Sol</hi> keepes his Dinner, and <hi>Mars</hi> ſhall happen to burne there his fingers.</p>
               <p>The laſt day, it is full Moone, then you ſhall finde many Cheſts that are full, but more hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low bellies and emptie Barnes, but bee patient for a while, for you ſhall ſhortly haue plentie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of all kinde of Fruites.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Julius.</head>
               <p>THe 7. th, being the laſt Quarter, ſo was <hi>Leo</hi> deliuered from the rage of <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Saturnus,</hi> vpon paſport giuen vnto them. Aſſoone as <hi>Iupiter</hi> came in <hi>Virgo,</hi> asked the Mayd with a heauie minde, where that the prouiſion of Corne was? and hee promiſed to ſend it within few dayes, and wiſhed that her Children that dwell in the Low-lands, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ouer-watring Riuers, ſhould not eate it Greene; which if they did, the moyſture of it ſhould ingender burning and hot Sickneſſes, and many thouſands ſhould dye before they ſhould come to the taſte of the Flower of the new Corne, of which the Catchers of the Crabbes ſhall haue a part, namely vpon the 52. 54. and 46. Degrees. And hee will neither ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2876:11"/>
the Maydens on the fieldes themſelues, of which many ſhall account themſelues happie, as giuing no ſucke, nor being troubled with children, neuertheleſſe, they will grieue much for their beloued which are gone to the warres, and other voyages.</p>
               <p>The 14. came <hi>Mars</hi> with the new Moone to <hi>Leo,</hi> deſiring aide of him before his death; the <hi>Lyon</hi> ſtanding in ſome need of him, began to giue eare vnto him: and when they were yet walking together, the Cannon began to thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whereupon theſe two friends caſt both their eyes downe, and ſeeing the play to goe on, it ſeemed that they tooke delight in it, for wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king yet in the Heauen, they looked very mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, and they ſeemed rather to be inclined to laughing then crying, and their Boyes vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this, beſides <hi>Saturnius</hi> (who was yet in <hi>Leo</hi>) they made together ſuch noiſe with laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the whole earth quaked: And it may be that this vnſatiable dire (thought to get his bellie full of Children) To be briefe, the wicked ſhall haue the vpper hand, but alas, they walke with the Deuill and the Death.</p>
               <p>The 21. came <hi>Sol</hi> likewiſe in <hi>Leo;</hi> I ſeeing that they were enlightened by the brightneſſe of the Sunne, it ſeemed vnto me, that the gods tooke pleaſure that mortall men ſet ſo one vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an other with ſlaſhing, ſtriking, murthering, and firing: yea, ſtonie hearts would haue cryed if they had ſeene the damps and vapours that were in <hi>Polonia, Germany, Italy, Spaine,</hi> and the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2876:12"/>
                  <hi>Lowe Countries: France</hi> and <hi>England</hi> being excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in which the Starres had not their will.</p>
               <p>The 23. being the firſt quarter, they were bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie about the burying of the dead, but they could not agree amongſt themſelues vpon the deuiſion of the goods of the dead: whereupon they tooke one another by the haire, although the Gouernours had forbidden it, for their bloud was too hotte. The Region turnes alſo much to the Weſt, ſo that it is likely that there is alſo ſomething to doe, and chiefly about the Zouth Sea, where the <hi>Griffons</hi> or gold-eaters dwell.</p>
               <p>The 30. was very perfectly by cleere Moone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine written with three croſſes, which <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> (being in <hi>Leo</hi>) could ſee very well, and was to drawe them very skilfully off as was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded vnto him; but he taking great delight in the ruine of another, he leapt preſently vp, and went amongſt the reſt, and threw cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Pedlers ſtall vnder the feet by a tricke which he had. Whereupon there came other which tooke the Wares preſently vp, and he ſet them at worke being fit for Warres, but conſumeth many men. But the new gouerning Godds make no difficultie therefore, and ſay, who is ſlaine he is paid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Auguſtus.</head>
               <p>THe 6. being full Moone, were both <hi>Mars, Saturnus, Venus, Sol,</hi> and <hi>Luna</hi> altogether appearing in the courſe of the Sunne, as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2876:12"/>
well by water as by land, with their burning Torches; and commanded <hi>Mercurie</hi> to conduct the Waggon in ſuch manner, that the Aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate or Speaker of the Husbandman was dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to ſay <hi>Quiſquis delirat plectuntur Achiui.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That is to ſay, the Boare muſt pay for the ill deedes, actions, and dycing, ill play of theſe great Maſters (which if it were but the Boare alone) for ſuch great Armadoes or Armies need not to be ſet forth to play onely the poore Boare, but it is to bring ſome great Maſters ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in or out of their Kingdome, vnder the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of this Zodiacke, for I finde none that will giue ouer or deſiſt: and concerning <hi>Iupiter</hi> himſelfe, he is as Herbinger gone before, to procure that <hi>Virgo</hi> ſhall haue ſomething to bring to the Table.</p>
               <p>The 12. ſo ſhall there bee a coniunction of <hi>Saturnus</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> and the operation of it ſhall be ſeene before 14. dayes runne at an end (or are expired.)</p>
               <p>The 14. being new Moone, ſo begin they to doe their operation, and that not onely by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnder <hi>Neptunus,</hi> but alſo by land vnder <hi>Mars,</hi> and chiefly in the Northerne lands of Europe, the Armies are marching in ſeuerall places, and the Husbandman lets his Plowe reſt, and the Shipper hoyſeth his Sayles vp, the one makes roome for the other, and that which the one hath gathered, the other conſumeth: to bee ſhort, the world goeth quite contrarie, and the Netherlanders themſelues alſo ſhall goe with
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2876:13"/>
their heads downewards, to diue after the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gold; others will goe to fill the ayre with their renowne, which ſtands as firme as a Caſtle in the skie: there ſhall alſo another come forth, which ſhall be deſirous to haue a Starre aſwell in heauen as his Confederates: but to be briefe, euery one ſtriue for the higher boord or place, whereupon there is a great ſtrife to happen, both betwixt Beaſts and Birds, and after the end of the battell, ſo ſhall the ayre be infected, by the noiſome ſmell of the dead carkaſſes.</p>
               <p>The 19. commeth <hi>Sol</hi> in <hi>Virgo,</hi> leauing yet ſome of the afore-mentioned Counſellers in <hi>Leo,</hi> where they are rayling being almoſt in a rage: And there ſhall without any doubt, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deſperate ſpirits be found; yea, aſwell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt beaſts as men.</p>
               <p>The 20. being the firſt quarter, ſo ſhall the coniunction before mentioned ſhew her ſelfe more plaine, and eſpecially towards the Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne Lands, <hi>Poland</hi> hath likewiſe to expect ſomething out of <hi>Sweden.</hi> Looke vpon the King of the <hi>Gotts,</hi> and <hi>Hungarie,</hi> which drinke other drinke: of <hi>Italy</hi> we haue ſpoken before, <hi>Spaine</hi> get ſhelles, and Signeur will couer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with Letice and Roſes (which is ſeene in <hi>Baetauia</hi> it ſelfe) and that in a laughing manner, but when the one laughs, ſo weepes the other, that is the courſe of this yeare.</p>
               <p>The 28. being full Moone began the ſtreames of the Ocean Sea to ceaſe, and to ſtand ſtill, to harken after the rumour that was ſpread abroad
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2876:13"/>
of the Sunne who ſhould turne his head to the South, leauing the Northerne quarters with many ſickneſſes and dead ones, but he ſhall keepe a certaine limited courſe, euen as the fierce thunders, and the hurlewindes doe: In the Eaſt and Weſt Indies ſhall the ſeruants of <hi>Mars</hi> fight, and <hi>Mars</hi> ſhall receaue a deadly wound, but recouer his health againe, <hi>Saturnus</hi> ſhall burne his head, by reaſon that his anger ſhall be greater, when he commeth in <hi>Virgo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>September.</head>
               <p>THe 4. being the laſt quarter, is <hi>Lucifer</hi> onely in <hi>Leo,</hi> he is to doe much hurt, and ſhall vſe ſuch cruelty, as <hi>Mars</hi> himſelfe neuer imagined; yea, he gets ſo much vantage, that he can ſhew his power according to his owne pleaſure, but I pitty them vpon whom it lights: And if his reigne might haue beene of any continuance, hee would haue deſtroyed the one 4. part of mankinde, and ſent them to the earth, to looke what is become of their Anceſtors. And thereupon, ſo ſhall the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines in <hi>Italy, Sicilia,</hi> and they alſo that are in the Eaſt and Weſt <hi>Indies</hi> caſt vp both fire and ſmoake; and there are likewiſe to happen fierce Thunder-bolts and Earthquakes, and other
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2876:14"/>
elementary alterations, which ſhall mightily mooue the world to her ſelfe and repent if it be not too late (according to the Prouerbe) to boyle a Poſſet when the man is dead: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore looke to it, it concerneth your owne ſelfe.</p>
               <p>The 12. is the new Moone, vpon Thurſday againſt the euening are both <hi>Sol, Iupiter, Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> in <hi>Virgo,</hi> being altogether very ſorie and heauie, and at the ſame time ſo groweth the Sunne darke vpon 52. degrees by the Line in the South, and vpon 51. to 54. on the North ſide of the Equinoctiall ſhall the blow be felt, ſo that <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spaine</hi> ſhall be in great danger. <hi>Mercurius</hi> as a ſwift Meſſenger, bringeth ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of a certaine battaile, and was therefore as ſorrie as a Souldier is, when a louſe of his falleth in the fire. It ſeemeth that the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Gods would faine put the Woolfes skinne off, and drawe the Sheepes skin on, and to ouer-rule <hi>Mars,</hi> ſeeing that he had play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuch a crooked or left-handed tricke, and deſired him to conſider what damage the Townes and Countries had receaued, and how much pretious bloud of man there was ſpilled: as likewiſe how much hurt mankinde had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by famine, miſerie, peſtilence, and the other plagues which the God of Gods appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto it.</p>
               <p>The 20. is the firſt quarter of the Moone, and you ſhall then finde out, that <hi>Mercurius</hi> is in <hi>Libra,</hi> to weigh ouer all the Merchandizes, but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2876:14"/>
the Meſſenger is too light, and the Iuſtice too meeke, not auoyding many wicked accidents which it could doe, for to doe ill, aydes to feed the war, and the warre makes ſome rich, but they reſemble the Beaſt which deuoures the gold, and the more it eates groweth more hungery, ſo that all will be ill, vnleſſe the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gators and ringleaders be ſet in the fore-front at the approach.</p>
               <p>The next day being the 21. commeth <hi>Sol</hi> in <hi>Libra,</hi> and makes both night and day of one length, but the goods and Lordſhips ſhall ſtill vnequally bee deuided.</p>
               <p>The 26. is full Moone, and <hi>Sol</hi> being in <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra</hi> ſhall be aboue the Netherlands, end borde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Countries which are neere it. Vpon this day, there ſhall in the euening about 9. of the clocke, a darkeneſſe on the Moone bee ſeene e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnder <hi>Piſces,</hi> what this ſignifieth ſhall the time ſhew. But it is certaine, that the learned hold it for an ill ſigne, and to preſage a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ruine, robberie, and violence, and cauſeth alſo ſome to die, but eſpecially them vnto whom it is ſhowne. But the wicked will not ceaſe to oppreſſe the innocent, and take no warning, and thinke on theſe plagues onely when they are ſleeping, and leaue all care to the Birds which haue ſmall legges.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:2876:15"/>
               <head>October.</head>
               <p>THe 4. it is the Laſt quarter, <hi>Saturnius</hi> departs then from <hi>Leo,</hi> which is a good ſigne, but neuertheleſſe, there are many things heere before mentioned, which ſhall doe their operation in this moneth, the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience it ſelfe teacheth this vnto vs, and it needs no proofe being here before expreſſed, and eſpecially in the yeare of 22. and 23. Now vpon the ſame day aforementioned, ſo ſhall <hi>Saturne, Iupiter,</hi> and <hi>Mercurie</hi> be in <hi>Virgo,</hi> and <hi>Mars, Venus, Sol,</hi> and <hi>Luna</hi> in <hi>Libra,</hi> which are good Signes of peace, and without doubt ſo ſhall the one or the other Potentate bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered of the Warre which ſhall goe to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</p>
               <p>The 12. it is new Moone, and then goe all the afore-mentioned Signes equally one with another, which happens but ſeldome, and will without queſtion preſage ſomething, but that will expect ſuch a time as it was in the yeare 1618. (in which I wrote this) he ſhall be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken: But let vs ſet this aſide and behold o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confluences, and Signes, which are not knowne to the common people; And I finde that at this time there ſhall many places be fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon the 45. degrees about the Riuer of <hi>Donaw,</hi> and the fields betwixt the Riuers of <hi>Elbe</hi> and of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and they which dwell
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2876:15"/>
about the Maſe and the Scheld ſhall ſee the ſmoake ariſing thence. The Weſt Indians ſhall likewiſe about the ſame time ſee many Sayles or armed Shippes (as well in the North as South Sea) being loaden with hope; the Braſilians ſhall alſo receaue a gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at the ſame time.</p>
               <p>The 19. being the firſt quarter, is <hi>Sol,</hi> in <hi>Scorpio,</hi> and bringeth this afore-mentioned Company in this order; yea, euen by a tyding which commeth out of the Eaſt Indies, ſome degrees in the South by the Equinoctiall line, declaring, that both heauen and earth were full of the rumour and certaine newes of the miſerable ſtate of the Romane Empire; for the Gold Mines are deſtroyed about the ſame time, and <hi>Neptunus,</hi> the friend of <hi>March</hi> hath lent his helping hand too it. And the Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders (according to his relation) carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſo, both in the Eaſt and Weſt Indies, that the Spaniards ſhall feele it. Vpon the ſame they went in ſuch manner to worke, as if <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Saturnus</hi> would before their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture turne all topſie turnie, caſting all things to the ground, and amongſt other, a Nation that carrieth the red <hi>Lyon,</hi> which made a great breach with other that carried <hi>Luna</hi> in their armes.</p>
               <p>The 29. raigned yet all the former Planets, and ſought to effect that which was intended, but warre going an vncertaine time on, aſwell
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2876:16"/>
by water as by land, many fled in the meane time from the one Land to the other; ſome to eſcape the warres, others the Plague, and ſome the dearth and famine. And euen about this time, ſo ſhall there fall vpon the Earth much fire, &amp; flames riſing from the poyſoned and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed Starres, the place on which it falleth are to be ſhunned, for this is a ſigne of the Plague which is out of the Northerne Lands, to come to the Weſt and Southweſt.</p>
               <p>Theſe are all heauie Thunder-bolts, and ſhowres, after which is many times a faire Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine ſeene, and the like ſhall happen to ſome Nations, of which was almoſt no helpe.</p>
               <p>About 150. yeares agoe was likewiſe an alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in Chriſtendome (the Planets ſtanding then as they ſtand now) but it euaniſhed quickly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Nouember.</head>
               <p>THE ſecond day after All-Saintes is the laſt quarter of the Moone, the Sunne is yet in the poyſoning <hi>Scorpio,</hi> and you ſhall ſeldome as long as he abides there, haue any good iſſue, and hee ſhall chiefely annoy them, which are neereſt vnto him, for vpon the ſame time, viz. <hi>In illo tempore,</hi> went great for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces out of <hi>Affrica</hi> into <hi>Spaine,</hi> and there ſhall
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2876:16"/>
likewiſe a great number goe to the Northerne lands, as alſo to <hi>Gallia, Batavia,</hi> and <hi>Hungaria,</hi> but they ſhall not haue any good ſucceſſe, as the Hiſtories ſhall declare at large. And when I conſider the matter well, ſo finde I that yet to ſtand firme, which is written in the great <hi>Opera</hi> to the full in an ample manner, but it is not for euery mans dyet, but I will put my finger in the earth, and ſmell in what land I am. But it is enough for the learned.</p>
               <p>The 10. is full Moone, and <hi>Luna</hi> is in <hi>Scorpio,</hi> and <hi>Saturnus</hi> and <hi>Iupiter</hi> in <hi>Virgo,</hi> but <hi>Iupiter</hi> is very heauie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> being in <hi>Libra,</hi> although they make yet little or nothing of the matter, are neuertheleſſe better now then in the laſt Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer to be ſpoken withall. Hauing now taken the hight of ſome <hi>Corpora</hi> that raigne. I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue that there will be yet a great alteration on the foot of the <hi>Alpes,</hi> whence both the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, namely the <hi>Rhine</hi> and the <hi>Donaw</hi> take their beginning: as likewiſe along the Strand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>France</hi> behinde <hi>Sicilia</hi> (perhaps <hi>Sicilia</hi> and <hi>Portugal</hi>) and in other ſtrange Countries which are oppoſed againſt them. There ſhall likewiſe many riſe in the North about <hi>Polonia</hi> and <hi>Lituania</hi> along the Eaſterne Sea, and goe towards the South.</p>
               <p>The 17. is the firſt quarter: And then ſhall there an Armie be deuided to ſurpriſe another, but the deſigne ſhall partly be diſcouered, the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2876:17"/>
fight will not end without ſhedding of blood, and there are many materials to be left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde, although the aſſalted ſhall not quite be ouerthrowne. Vpon the ſame time is there likewiſe ſome ſodaine exploit to bee made in manner of an excurſion in <hi>Lituania,</hi> and <hi>Tarta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> neuertheleſſe, men ſhall be ſolde as beaſts.</p>
               <p>On the 19. is the Sunne in <hi>Sagitarius,</hi> and it will then mend ſhortly, for the great courage and heate of many ſhall be ſpent, whereby the warres will ſlacken and decreaſe.</p>
               <p>The 24. is full Moone, and diuers aſpects of the Planets are come towards the South, and Southweſt, comming there out of the Eaſt; the North-landers ſhall be glad therefore, and fill their Cheſts with bootie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>December.</head>
               <p>THe third being the laſt Quarter, ſo was <hi>Mars, Iupiter,</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> in the Aſpect, which will cauſe a great alteration; for ſeeing that <hi>Saturnius, Luna,</hi> and <hi>Iupiter</hi> were found in <hi>Virgo,</hi> there ſhall be ſome great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that ſhall become faint-hearted, and be deſirous to lay their Armes downe, to mooue thereby other to doe the like, thinking that they will dance as he pipes before them. But his leſſer will not condeſcend to it, ſeeing that <hi>Mars</hi> was on the ſame day yet in <hi>Scorpio,</hi> and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2876:17"/>
gaue to him a great and manly courage, and ſaid that it was now the right time to take re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge of the Enemie. Moreouer, ſo was <hi>Neptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> likewiſe come by the ſhadow of <hi>Luna</hi> vnder the <hi>Tropicus</hi> to giue ayde vnto him, that is to ſay, that the Heathens which pray to the Moone, ſhall ayde the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> (to hitte the naile right on the head) and the proofe or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration is to be ſeene on the croſſe Starre.</p>
               <p>The 5. is <hi>Saturne, Iupiter, Mars</hi> and <hi>Mercurius</hi> in the fourth aſpect, and <hi>Mercurius</hi> ſitting on the Sterne, ſeekes by policie and craft to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct the Ship into another port, yea, vnder the Maiden Brit.</p>
               <p>The 10. it being new Moone, and the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters very high in ſeuerall parts of the world, The Sunne being yet in <hi>Sagitarius,</hi> cauſeth ſtrange fortunes and accidents, both in <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> and <hi>Polonia,</hi> and likewiſe in other parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> but eſpecially about the Riuer of <hi>Rhine. Venus</hi> being at the ſame time very heauy, was in the <hi>Ram,</hi> and cryed then for the loſſe of ſome of her louers which ſhe had in former times, but it went with her as the Prouerbe ſaith, the cryes are all lowde and the teares hotte, true loue is ſoone forgot, and returned ſo againe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs with a fainted heauineſſe. <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Mercurius;</hi> which are in the fourth Aſpect, with diuers other Coniunctions and Aſpects preſage that it is a dangerous and deceitfull time, as will appeare ſhortly vpon the hight of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2876:18"/>
                  <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> ſo that all the Northerne lands ſhall haue reaſon to looke to themſelues, for there is ſome danger hanging ouer their head, and chiefely ouer them where the warre was this laſt Summer.</p>
               <p>The 17. it is the firſt quarter, and <hi>Luna</hi> in <hi>Aries:</hi> when the Sunne ſhall goe from <hi>Aries,</hi> then ſhall many things (of which wee haue ſpoken here before) be manifeſted and appeare, and eſpecially concerning the <hi>Indies,</hi> to the great griefe of the Bird of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> or of the <hi>Eagle,</hi> and to the ioy and comfort of them that dwell in the Wood of vnmercifulneſſe: whereby is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, <hi>Batauia</hi> or <hi>Gallia inter Rhenum,</hi> and their next neighbours ſhall bee ſorie becauſe they proſper and doe well, but their heauineſſe will ſhortly turne in ioy, when they ſhall alſo receaue ſome part of the bootie. But ſhall ſtill thinke that the meate is fatter in their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours diſhes then in their owne.</p>
               <p>The 19. is <hi>Sol</hi> in <hi>Capricornus</hi> and <hi>Saturnius</hi> (the Ruler of this yeare) in <hi>Libra,</hi> and ſhall looſe there his Gouernment, and ſhall the next yeare not bee ſet ſo high, by reaſon of his crueltie. Hereupon, ſhall the plague decreaſe in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> and euery one ſhall haue time to inroll his dead ones, which died within the laſt foure mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, both by warre and her ordinary fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers.</p>
               <p>The 24. it is full Moone, and then ſhall the perſecution againſt an innocent Nation ceaſe,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2876:18"/>
whereupon, if ſome other which are of a worſe humour and life, doe not mend themſelues, <hi>Mars</hi> when hee commeth from <hi>Scorpio</hi> ſhall ſhoot a poyſoned Dart into their intralls. You ſhall yet before the end of this yeare, heare ſtrange tydings, both out of <hi>Greece, Perſia</hi> and <hi>Turkie,</hi> and ſhall tend to great preiudice of the Bird of <hi>Iupiter.</hi> There are yet other things to be told, but ſeeing that mine Incke begins to freeze, and my Parchment to ſhrinke, I will therefore make an end, and commend you to the moſt mercifull God.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
